Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know the secretion of melatonin
appears to progressively decline with age,
dropping as much as 70%
between middle age and older age?
Here’s our first story.
Some experts recommend melatonin
as a first-line agent
to treat insomnia
in older adults.
The World Sleep Society
disagrees
due to its low efficacy.
Subjectively,
people report better sleep,
though objectively,
a meta-analysis of studies
found that melatonin
only helped people
get to sleep 4 minutes faster
and extend
overall sleep duration
by about 13 minutes.
If you do want to try melatonin
to help with sleep,
older adults are advised
to use the smallest
effective dose
an hour before bedtime,
starting perhaps
at 0.3 milligrams.
The 12-milligram supplements
on the market
could produce levels
in the bloodstream
that can be
two hundred times higher
than normal nightly levels,
which raises safety concerns.
After all,
melatonin used to be known
as the anti-gonad hormone,
with human-equivalent doses
of just a milligram or two
reducing the size of sex organs
and impairing fertility
in laboratory animals.
Furthermore,
due to poor regulation
of dietary supplements,
in the U.S.,
you never know
what you're gonna be getting.
An analysis
of thirty-one different brands
of melatonin supplements
found that the actual
melatonin content varied
up to nearly 500 percent
compared to what was listed
on the bottle.
Even within a single brand,
different lots
of the same product
suffered similar variability.
Given that there is
no guarantee
of the strength or purity
of melatonin supplements,
many countries have banned
over-the-counter melatonin,
making it prescription-only
so authenticity
could be ensured.
U.S. citizens can get
certified melatonin
by sending a prescription
to an online Canadian pharmacy
(though it's
technically illegal)
or can get melatonin
from their diet.
Interestingly, the rise
in melatonin blood levels
or metabolites in the urine
consistently exceeds
the amount of melatonin
that's actually ingested
in these foods.
You can even get a spike
in melatonin
after eating fruit
that doesn't even appear
to have any detectable
melatonin at all.
The answer to the puzzle
may lie in the gut.
The first site
outside the pineal gland
where melatonin production
was discovered
was the human appendix.
Although we now know
melatonin can be produced
throughout the body,
the greatest accumulation
appears to be
in the gastrointestinal tract,
estimated to contain more than
400 times more melatonin
than the pineal gland.
So, perhaps the consumption
of certain foods
can cause the release
of some of this bounty
into the bloodstream.
This may be
how magnesium supplements
(500 milligrams a day
for eight weeks)
was able to improve
sleep quality and quantity
over placebo, given the effect
was accompanied by a rise
in melatonin levels.
More intriguing are its
purported anti-aging benefits.
In addition to regulating sleep
and our circadian rhythms
(when properly timed
it can be used
to treat jet lag),
melatonin can have antioxidant
and anti-inflammatory
properties.
However, secretion of melatonin
appears to progressively
decline with age,
dropping as much as 70 percent
between middle and older age.
This has led some to speculate
that "aging is a syndrome of
relative melatonin deficiency
resulting from
the gradual failure
of the pineal gland."
A variety
of age-related diseases
such as Alzheimer's
are associated
with particularly low levels
of melatonin,
but we have yet to determine
if this is a cause
or consequence of disease.
Melatonin supplementation
extends the lifespan
of fruit flies but shortens
the lifespan of C. elegans.
Mice that have had
their pineal glands removed
appeared to age more rapidly,
but when put to the test,
melatonin prolonged survival
of some strains of mice,
but shortened the lives
of others (by inducing cancer).
So, are we more like
New Zealand black mice
or Bagg albino mice?
Sometimes
the same research group
went on to publish
opposite results,
showing melatonin
both increasing
and decreasing lifespan.
Not surprisingly,
a meta-analysis found
no overall effect
when all of the mouse studies
were considered together.
In rats, melatonin
significantly improved survival,
but so did
a melatonin-blocking drug.
In our next story, we ask
is six hours of sleep enough?
Conventional wisdom has it
that over the last 50 years
sleep duration has declined
in parallel with the increasing
prevalence of obesity,
suggesting that an epidemic
of sleep loss is associated with
the epidemic of weight gain.
Now, we have triple digit streaming
TV channels, smartphones,
and tablets to keep us entertained
well into the night.
"The hurry and excitement
of modern life is quite correctly
held to be responsible
for much of the insomnia,"
concluded one medical
journal editorial.
But that was an editorial
published in 1894.
Are we really sleeping
that much less?
Since 1905, sleep duration
in children and adolescents
has declined by a little
over an hour a night.
However, child labor wasn't
outlawed until 1938 though,
and so part of the explanation
may be due to the exhaustion
of sweating it out in the mines,
farms, and factories
in the early part of the last century.
Since 1970, youth sleep duration
has only declined about
15 minutes per night,
and it's not clear if sleep duration
in adults has changed much at all.
Based on 168 studies of objective
measurements of sleep duration,
instead of just self-report,
sleep duration in adults --
objective total sleep time --
has't changed much since 1960.
Since 2003, average sleep
duration in the United States
may have even gone up.
Now, of course, just because
we don't have evidence
that there's been a growing
epidemic of sleep deprivation
that doesn't necessarily mean
we're getting enough sleep.
Maybe we weren't getting enough
sleep 50 years ago either,
or since Edison's lightbulbs,
or since candles were
invented 5,000 years ago.
How might we determine
the optimal sleep duration?
One way would be to study
millions of people and see
how many hours a night is
associated with the longest lifespan.
Sleep is a great mystery.
A trait shared across animal species,
sleep must be of vital importance
to survive natural selection pressures
to eliminate such a vulnerable state.
Indeed, cringe-worthy
experiments have shown that
keeping animals awake long enough
is fatal within 11 to 32 days.
One of the functions of sleep that
has been elucidated in recent years
is the clearance of toxic
waste substances
that build up during the day
through a newly discovered
drainage system in the brain.
This could help explain why
those who routinely get
less than seven hours of sleep
at night may be at increased risk
of developing cognitive
disorders such as dementia.
Even a single all-nighter can
cause a significant increase
in beta amyloid accumulation
in critical brain areas,
a gummy substance implicated in the
development of Alzheimer's disease.
The lowest risk for developing
cognitive impairment was found
for those getting seven to
eight hours of sleep a night,
which is the same optimal range
found for diabetes risk,
based on 36 studies following
more than a million people.
The increased risk associated
with getting only six hours a night
compared to seven or eight
is comparable
to the increase in diabetes risk
linked to physical inactivity.
For death from all causes combined,
there's been more than 50 studies
following hundreds of thousands
of people for up to 34 years.
Sleeping too short and too long
are both associated
with cutting one's life short,
with the apparent sweet spot
at seven hours a night.
Seven hours may seem short,
but that may actually be
what's natural for our species.
Scientists studied three isolated
pre-industrial societies
across two continents and
found a surprising uniformity.
Despite no electric lighting
or gadgets,
they stayed up until
about three hours
after sunset and then
typically rose before dawn,
accumulating about a solid
six and a half hours of sleep
out of about seven and
a half hours in "bed."
A mechanism by which excess sleep
might be harmful remains elusive,
and so the association between
increased risk of death and disease
and sleeping nine or more hours
a night has been largely dismissed
as implausible.
Maybe its reverse causation,
sickness leading to more time
in bed instead of vice-versa,
or confounding factors
such as employment status.
After all, who gets to sleep in?
Those without a job to get to.
However, there is experimental
evidence showing negative
health effects from insufficient sleep.
So in terms of sleeping
in the sweet spot, aim for at least
seven hours of regular sleep a day.
Finally today,
we look at how one function of sleep may
be the clearance of toxic waste byproducts
through a newly discovered
drainage system in the brain.
Sleep is a great mystery.
A trait shared
across animal species,
sleep must be
of vital importance
to survive
natural selection pressures
to eliminate
such a vulnerable state.
Indeed, cringeworthy experiments
have shown
that keeping animals awake
long enough
can be fatal within
eleven to thirty-two days.
It turns out
sleep is of-the-brain,
by the brain,
and for the brain.
One function of sleep that has
been elucidated in recent years
is the clearance
of toxic waste byproducts
through a newly discovered
drainage system in the brain.
With the invention
of the encephalogram, EEG,
to measure brain wave activity,
the scientific world
was quickly disabused
of the notion that sleep was
a time of rest for the brain.
During certain stages of sleep
there is brain-wide activity
going on,
but what was
the brain actively doing?
More than 2,000 years ago,
Aristotle proposed that sleep
helps the body clean the blood.
Today, we know sleep may help
the body clean the brain.
Until 2012, we thought
that the brain was singular
among organs for recycling
nearly all of its own waste.
It had to,
since it was separated
from the rest of the body
by the blood-brain barrier.
But the barrier that keeps
toxins out of the brain
presumably keeps toxins in.
Then, in 2012,
a brain-wide
fluid transport network
was discovered,
termed the glymphatic system.
By microscopically tracking dye
injected into the brains
of mice,
scientists discovered
fluid-filled tunnels
surrounding blood vessels
in the brain.
The pressure wave
of arterial pulses
with every heartbeat
milks the fluid along
before eventually draining
into the cerebrospinal fluid
surrounding the brain.
What does this
have to do with sleep?
The whole system is only
really active when sleeping.
During wakefulness,
these tunnels are clamped down,
reducing glymphatic flow
by 90 percent.
The thought is the fluid shifts
might interfere
with targeted neurotransmitter
chemical communication
in the awake state.
So the biological need for sleep
may reflect the need
for the brain to enter
into a state to filter out
potentially neurotoxic waste
products like beta amyloid,
which is implicated
in Alzheimer's disease.
Perhaps this could help explain
why those who routinely get
fewer than seven hours of sleep
a night are at increased risk
of developing cognitive
disorders such as dementia.
Randomizing individuals
to have their sleep disrupted
by a series of beeps
administered through headphones
in a sleep lab
increases amyloid levels,
whereas improving sleep,
by treating sleep apnea patients
with CPAP, for example,
improves slow wave activity,
deep sleep, and appears
to lower amyloid levels.
PET scans show
even a single all-nighter
can cause
a significant increase
in accumulation of beta amyloid
in critical brain areas.
The problem is that
glymphatic brain filtration
appears to decline with aging.
Old mice only have
10 to 20 percent
the glymphatic function
of young mice.
This could be due
to a number of factors.
As we age,
we experience less
of the deep, slow wave sleep,
the type of sleep during
which brain waste clearance
appears to be the most active.
Further contributing
to the stagnancy,
our arteries tend
to stiffen as we age,
reducing the pulsations
that drive the glymphatic pump.
That also offers
one potential explanation
as to why hypertension
is tied to dementia.
The thickening of artery walls
with high blood pressure
also has a stiffening effect.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.